Hello.
Thank you all for joining
CS 25 Transformers today.
For today's talk we have Ming
Ding, a research scientist
at Zhipu AI based in Beijing.
He obtained his bachelor's
and doctoral degrees
at Tsinghua University,
and he does research
on multimodal generative models
and pretraining technologies.
He has led or participated
in the research
works about multimodal
generative models,
such as CogView and CogVideo,
and multimodal understanding
models such as
CogVLM and CogAgent.
For today's attendance,
the attendance form
is up on the course website.
And if you have any questions,
ask them through Slido,
S-L-I-D-O. And for the code,
you just have to input "CS 25."
Thank you, Ming,
for today's talk,
and I'm going to
pass it off to you.
Thank you for the
instructors of CS 25.
I was very happy to
give a talk in Stanford
University about
multimodality in pretraining.
And actually, I have checked
all the previous talks in CS 25,
and they are really
diverse topics.
Someone shared the
intuitions in their research
about pretraining, someone
shared recent works
about maybe MOE and
some other technicals.
Actually, I'm working in a large
language model company in China,
and our company
working on pretraining.
And maybe there's lots
of different areas
from a large language model
and multimodality model
and [INAUDIBLE] model,
diffusion, and text-to-speech,
something like that.
So I lead all the multimodality
model research in Zhipu AI,
so I will share lots of
different topics in this talk.
Some of them may be not very
familiar to you, so yeah,
it's OK.
But you can get more
information on a different area.
I will talk about several
aspects of transformers,
and I will generally follow the
history of large language model
and say why are we here.
It's about the large language
model introduction and history.
And how did we get here?
It's about some
practical techniques
for training large
language models.
And what are we working on?
It's about the last one year
of the real language models
and other techniques
in the papers
of all the visual
language model community.
And finally, I will talk about
some possible and valuable
direction for research
in multimodality.
OK.
I will share three moments,
I think the most important
three moments in the
development of language model.
The first moment is
called birth moment.
Actually, I got into
the area at this moment.
It's very honored that I'm
among the first group of people
who published papers on the
next year, the [INAUDIBLE],
when BERT came out.
And at that time, things is--
we don't really know what
is language modeling.
So at that time,
nearly all the people
are talking about how can we get
a better self-supervised method
in our machine.
At that time, a
common opinion is
masked language model is as
good as understanding the text.
And GPT, the
autoregressive model,
is better for text generations.
And T5 maybe can do them
both but is redundant.
And that's true.
But nowadays, we all say
that GPT has now a nearly--
silver bullet or other anarchy.
Sometimes the things
changes, and we
will back from that
time point and know
how the language
model things and how
we got more and more knowledge
about language model.
So at that time, the--
I'm also among one
of them who want
to develop a new self-supervised
learning method for [INAUDIBLE].
We published a paper
called GLM, and we
want to unify the BERT,
the masked language
model, and the
autoregressive model,
and T5 in decoder-only style.
Actually, the method
is very simple.
We just select a
part of the sequence
and only do autoregressive
modeling during this sequence.
So if we select the mask
area as all the sequence,
it become a GPT.
And part of them,
it becomes BERT.
So that's a method we
found very efficient.
And because we train it, it's
like a BERT, it's about 15%
of the masked area, and they
perform better than BERT.
We trained it as a GPT.
It perform the same as GPT.
It's very promising.
The second moment I
think is very important
is the GPT-3 moment.
It tells us the scaling
law is very important.
So you can design
different architectures,
define different laws,
different self-supervised tasks
and different methods to
schedule different models,
but the performance maybe
has some upper bound.
But so if you add
more compute, you
can get a guaranteed
performance improvement.
You can predict the
result's perplexity
based on the fitted curve.
So at that time, the
language modeling
has become more and
more engineering.
If you have find
a very good point,
you train a language model.
If you want to scale it
and your boss give you
four times of monies, you can
buy four times the compute.
You just assign the compute
four more parameters or training
more tokens.
This is called scaling law.
They tell you how you can
assign different potential
of your monies.
So at that time, the
language model don't really
need some architectural
innovation or algorithm
innovation, so it's become
a engineering thing.
And the third moment, I
think, which is more important
is called ChatGPT moment.
At that moment, it tells
us a very important fact
is task adaptation is cheap.
And what is very important is
the knowledge from pretraining.
This is a very bitter lesson.
So I have told you
that at that time,
we designed different losses,
different architectures,
but the aim of design
different losses
is to perform different tasks.
For example, the autoregressive
model cannot fill in the blank
in the sequence, but
GLM and BERT can,
so we use different
pretraining task.
But currently, we know that the
task adaptation is very cheap.
You just need to fine
tune your language model
at the final period.
The only important thing
is your pretraining loss.
The last figure is
from InstructGPT.
This is actually the paper
about ChatGPT and how can
we align a pretrained
model to a chat model.
It told that the alignment can
give a very huge improvement
on human preference compared to
the original pretrained language
model.
And the right figure is actually
a recent paper in our company.
It tells us a very
important fact.
Maybe it's intuitive.
The fact is the performance
of downstream task
is only related to the
loss of pretraining.
And it's not directly relevant
to the model size, which
means if a large model which a
very high loss because of lack
of training.
And a small model, we
train more and reach
the same level of loss.
They performed exactly the
same in the downstream tasks.
So the so-called
emergent ability
and some other maybe ability,
strange rumors are not true.
Actually, the ability is not
from the number of parameters
of language model.
It's actually only relevant to
the loss of your language model.
So all the language model
became a game of curve fitting.
This is actually the
current situation
of language model research.
So there's also some technical
details of large language model.
Even we know it's
not curve fitting,
but there's a lot
of important things.
So back from some basics and
talk about the transformer
architecture.
A very interesting thing is
the most important improvements
nowadays are still from the
first author of the transformer
paper, the Noam, and maybe
from his other papers.
So actually, the real
innovation in the architectures
is very small.
I can summarize some common
adaptation on transformer
currently.
First is decoder only.
The original transformer is a
encoder-decoder architecture,
so it's redundant because
the encoder and the decoder
should learn how to
understand the task
from different parameters.
So it's redundant.
And currently we only care about
decoder-only architectures.
The second one is
pre-layer norm.
In the original
transformer layer,
the layer norm is after
the residual connection.
It's called a posterior norm.
And currently, we usually
use pre-layer norm.
The rotary position embedding
is something very special
because it's not
published from a paper.
It's not.
It's published from
a Chinese blog.
But currently, it has
proven very efficient.
And the group query
attention is actually
from another paper of Noam.
It can save the
inference memory.
And GLU warrant
is also from Noam.
It's just a
replacement of the MLP.
And mixture-of-expert is
actually also from Noam's paper.
And you can use the same
FLOPs, small parameter
to get better performance.
So this is what's the
current and most of the ones
open-source language model, the
architecture of most advanced
open-source language model.
For example, Llama.
OK.
We know there's
architecture, but how
to train this transformer
is also very important.
We need to prepare
a very powerful code
base to train the
large language model.
So the first choice
is called DeepSpeed.
It's a library from Microsoft.
And some of the most
important optimization method
is from a paper called
ZeRO from DeepSpeed group.
Several years ago, some
of us not really know
how to train a very large model,
how to efficiently train them,
but ZeRO give us some advices.
For example, we can find
the most memory consumption
is actually the Adam states.
The optimizer
states, you must keep
it's for position as a float.
And the master weight
is also a float.
The parameter and gradient,
you can keep it high precision,
and you can have a fast
computation and save memories.
But the ZeRO1 can scatter the
master weight and optimizer
state into all the
data parallel racks.
So if you have more
racks, more GPU cards,
you just use less GPU
memory for each rank.
Another important technique is
called activation checkpointing.
It's actually recall the
intermediate state and recompute
going backward.
So we don't really need to
record all the computation flow
graph.
We just need to record
some of the hidden states.
It's reduce all the
activation from many layers
into one layers.
And there's other methods to
reduce the memory consumption.
For example, ZeRO2
CPU offload, which
means you can offload
some GPU memory to CPU.
And ZeRO3, also called
fully-sharded data parallel.
You can just shard your
model into different cards.
And when you use the parameter,
you gather this parameter
from the other racks.
So all of this method
is very complicated,
but the DeepSpeed library have
already give a very clean API
to use it.
So currently, it's not very hard
to train a very large language
model efficiently.
And Megatron is
another framework
to train large language models.
It is also the most
valuable framework
to train your super
large language
model with more than
100 billion parameters.
It use another set of
optimization method.
The first is called
tensor parallel.
The tensor parallel splits
the hidden sides and heads
into different ranks, and
it calls an additional
or reduce for attention and MLP
but reduce the other parameters,
consumption and
computing consumption
into different TP ranks.
The pipeline parallel
is to split the layers
into different ranks.
And it also introduces
bubbles in pipeline.
And there are some method,
for example, interleaved
and ZeroBubble to
remove this consumption.
Maybe if you want to train your
very large language model one
day, you need to learn about
all this kind of system things,
because the current large
language model training is
actually engineering work.
MLP is not very important.
The important thing is ML6.
So another very important
thing is long context.
It's actually
lossless long context,
which means we don't
use sparse attention
or other methods to change
the full attention behavior.
The current info how
to train long context
is beyond the imagination
for AI guys five years ago.
The last figure is
actually my paper
when I published several
years ago in NeurIPS.
At that time, there's no
such thing like GPT-3.
There's only BERT.
So this paper is
actually very complicated
to schedule two
different BERTs to mimic
the retrieval, rehearsal,
and forecast process
in working memory or human to
let the model to understand
very long context step by step.
But actually, we can see that we
can use different system level
technicals to understand
very long contexts.
For example, more
than 100,000 length.
It's full attention.
So it's just different
from several years ago.
And many things is
super simplified
because of this improvement.
A key technique is
called context parallel,
which means we split the
sequence into different ranks
and use a ring attention or
Ulysses and other technicals
to finish the attention.
And there's a library
called TransformerEngine,
and all this function is
warped in this library.
And we need to handle the
load balance of the attention
to make everyone have
the same computation.
So this is actually change
lots of different research
and applications of [INAUDIBLE].
For example, we summary
and it's trying some facts
from the documents several
years ago using BM25
or another retrieval method.
And currently we can just use a
transformer and full attention
to get the information
and understand it.
It's a quite
important improvement.
So using this very
powerful Infra,
we can train very
large language models.
And for the alignment,
the first period
is called SFT,
Supervised Fine Tuning.
It's actually a
very ordinary fine
tuning for language model
on high-quality data.
And the high-quality data is
usually from human annotation
This human annotation is
not just for sourcing.
You need to hear experts
from different domains who
write these high-quality
answers to train the model.
For example, if you want
the model to write some code
and explain the code in
a very formatted way,
you need to hire a very
experienced programmer
to write some examples to
teach this language model.
It's not just crowdsourcing.
This is quite different from
the previous human annotation.
We can also extract the
question-answer pairs
from more powerful models like
GPT-4 Turbo to train our model.
But this is actually
not alone by OpenAI,
so you cannot use this method
to develop a model to competing
with them.
But actually, if
for research, you
don't worry about
using that method,
well, now, we have
surpassed GPT-4,
because there's a paper called
Weak-to-Strong Generalization.
And recall what
I said just now--
what's really important
is your pretraining loss.
If your pretraining loss is
lower than your teacher model,
you can also surpass
your teacher model,
even you use SFT data
from your teacher model.
And another period of
alignment is called RLHF.
It use reinforcement
learning from human feedback
to improve the model.
But actually, the most
common open-language model
didn't use this method.
The main reason is PPO is
very hard to implement.
It could be very
powerful if your reward
model is good enough,
but not easy to train.
So there's some
more easy method.
And most open-source language
models, they use DPO method.
It's from paper from Stanford.
And we only need some preference
pairs and this formula
to update your model.
You don't really
need a reward model.
You don't really need a reward
model, you just need some pairs.
Maybe this pair should some
on-policy pairs, but yeah.
But it's much simpler
and also very powerful.
So these are basics of
how to train a language
model currently.
And it seems like it's
nothing about MLP.
It's actually a
party of ML6 guys.
So what are the LLM
pretrainers doing
is actually the most
important things is data.
Currently, the data cleaning,
filtering, synthesizing
is the most important thing of
all the large language model
company, which is a open secret.
So the training
infra is actually
a bit-- it's basically what I
said in the last several slides.
Maybe there's some other
more advanced method,
but the improvement is maybe
20% or something like that.
But if you have a
better pretraining data,
the performance of your
language model is quite obvious.
The language model,
we're told by the media
it's most one thing.
But actually, most
of the ML engineering
in large language model company
is actually cleaning the data.
So is this something a Stanford
graduate student should do?
Maybe someone seen as very low.
I want to design some new
algorithm architectures.
This is rare ML research.
But I have opinion that
the data, the algorithm,
and the architecture can
transform to each other.
So the data is
most general form.
But sometimes if you
don't have enough compute,
it could be very hard to
fit this kind of data.
And the algorithm is
very hard to implement
and not very general.
The architecture, it's hard
to perform what you want.
Designing new
architecture is very hard.
I will take a multi-hop question
answering task as an example.
The right figure
is from the CogQA.
It's also one of my papers
when I was a PhD student.
It's actually about a task to--
we have very complex question
and we need to find the task.
So the task finds the answer
from several documents,
but you need to find
the chain reasoning
between different documents
to get the final answer.
So at that time, I
propose a method.
It involved a broad and
graph neural network
is very complicated.
And finally, I got a
very good performance,
and 10 points better
than the previous method.
But yeah, this is actually
some algorithm or architecture
innovation.
It's very fancy and get very
high score in ACL review.
But there's some
other concurrent work
that use MCTS, the Monte
Carlo Tree Search and BERT
and something like that.
It looks like a
algorithm-level innovation
to solve this problem.
But currently, this problem
can be easily solved
by a very long context GPT and
chain-of-thought reasoning.
If you include nearly all the
documents into your contexts,
you don't need any things like
graph neural network or MCTS
to jump between the documents.
You have all the
contacts, and you can just
finish using channel sort.
It's a data-level solution.
So the data-level solution is,
of course, the most simple one
because you just add the data
into your training corpus,
and you can just finish
this task while not
affect other tasks.
So the data cleaning,
filtering, exercising
is not a very easy work, and it
actually very important view--
important to do this.
We should transform our
view of data and algorithms,
our entire chart, to
fit the current AI.
So I have introduced
some knowledge
about both the
language models, so I
will jump into the second
part, which is visual language
models in the past one year.
So the past one year, we have
seen the visual language models
jump from nearly very silly one
to our currently very powerful
ones.
So I will start from BLIP-2,
which is actually maybe,
I think, the first
work to bridge the CLIP
and can train a large language
model to give the language
model the ability to
understand the images.
Actually, if we have
an image encoder
from CLIP and the large
language model from anywhere.
So you can just insert,
on our transformer, called
a Q-former to extract some
important features from image
encoder and insert these
features into large language
model.
But the space of image features
and text features is different,
so the Q-former is trainable.
You'll need lots
of text-image pairs
and align the space
of image features
and the language and
text features the space.
The Q-former actually did this.
But there is a more simple
[INAUDIBLE] of called LLaVA.
It's actually don't use a
simple projection weight
to transform the vision encoder,
the feature from vision encoder
into the features in the
language model input.
So it's quickly become the
most popular architecture
of vision language models.
CogVLM is a work from our group.
The motivation of CogVLM is to
keep all the language behavior
while we add language--
image understanding ability
to the language model.
For LLaVA-- for the
previous method,
you actually can train
the language model
and get a better
performance, but it's
about multimodality task.
The language
ability of the model
will be reduced if
you train the language
model during the
text-image alignment.
So we first use
our vision experts
to add new parameters
in the backbone,
and the vision experts only
deal with the image features.
And the original weights
in feedforward layers
and the matrix, they're
always original task features.
So the original behavior
of language model is kept,
and we add lots
of new parameters
to train and get a
better performance
of multi-modality models.
So CogVLM achieves a
state-of-art performance
of several benchmarks, including
image captioning, grounding,
and VQA and some other visual
language model benchmarks.
And it's also open source,
so you can download it
from our GitHub.
Last month I found that CogVLM
is downloaded more than 500,000
times in the last month, so I
think it's already helped lots
of people.
And CogAgent here, another
works from our group.
It's use a different
architectures
because we want high resolution
with cross attention.
Why it's cross attention?
Because we don't want to--
we just want a
high-resolution input.
I don't want to let
all the hidden size
data as thin as
the language model
hidden size, which
is very large.
So we use cross attention to
deal with the low resolution.
The high resolution channels,
it's slightly complicated,
but the performance
is very good.
We can find-- this
model, they actually
trained it to be a web agent.
And it's just take
screenshots as input,
and it will perform different
operation on the screenshot.
For example, this is an example
for a search, the last year's
best paper in CVPR.
So we ask the model
these questions.
It told me you need to type
the best paper of CVPR 2023
in the box at this position.
And step by step, finally
we gather information.
And we can also use this
method to book some tickets
or perform some other tasks.
This is also open source.
Some other popular architecture
is about varied language
modeling and includes Vary.
It's actually an ensemble
of different vision features
as input.
And it's largely improved
the OCR performance.
But what I want to
stress is most--
once the Vary
language model GLM-4V,
we actually use a more
simple architecture.
It's actually a small
adaptation upon LLaVA.
We just replaced the
projection rate of LLaVA
into a stride convolution to
support high-resolution input
but keep the computation
in language model.
And using this architecture, we
can train the vision language
model mixed with the text.
And finally, we get
a good performance.
We can say that GLM-4V can, on
the power of GPT-4V or Gemini
or Claude3, and it performed
better in OCR benchmarks,
for example, document QA.
And it's perform much
better at Chinese OCR.
This is an example of our
most advanced GLM-4V model.
You can download our app
from this chatglm.cn website.
This is actually a very
hard to recognize draft,
and it's also a meme.
The model can analyze
it very accurately
and can translate
what is really right.
You can experience our model.
It's totally free
from this website.
OK.
We have some introduction about
vision language understanding.
It's more about engineering,
but it's multi-modality.
And another half of the
vision language research
about image
generation and is also
very relevant to transformers.
So I will also introduce the
rule about image generation.
Three or four years
ago, we already
know the GPT is very powerful.
So we want to autoregressively
modeling the text generation
for using the GPT architecture.
So this is the work of CogView.
It's also my work at 2022, '21.
It's a very simple
framework because we
know that GPT can only predict
multinomial distribution,
so we need to find
some method to train
the image in a discrete way.
There is a, maybe 2020, there's
a paper called iGPT from OpenAI.
It's trained directly
on the pixel level
for autoregressive modeling.
But the sequence is very
long, so you cannot train very
high-resolution images.
So we can reinforce the
training image tokenizer.
It's actually a VQ way
to discrete your image
into several tokens.
And you prepare the
sequence of a text image
as the text first,
image later, and you
can use GPT to train
these kind of segments.
And finally, during
the inference,
you first impose the text
and then predicts token
by token in the image, and
you can generate some image.
This is a very simple idea and
a concurrent work called Dall-E,
and the most
powerful work called
Parti is from the same idea.
We know that we generate
an image using GPT.
So a very natural
idea is, can we
achieve some universal modeling
for vision language tasks?
So if we just tokenize the
image just like the text,
we can generate image, we can
generate text from the image,
we can generate image from
text, and only generate text.
So this is a very neutral idea.
And I also did this in CogVL too
maybe two years ago, and yeah.
The other reason it's also very
simple is just in the sequence,
you change different position
of text and image sequence.
If first text then image
and you mask all the things
as text-to-image generation,
you force image then text,
it's image captioning.
And you can also get other
formats like masked auto-encoder
or something like that.
But the problem is when you
compare this universal modeling
system to diffusion or visual
language modeling with a vision
language model, you will
find the image generation
is worse than the diffusion and
very slow compared to diffusion.
For image understanding
it performed worse
than vision language model,
because when you transform
your image into discrete
tokens, lots of information
is lost during this process.
So the performance is worse
than the vision language model.
So using this method, you can
achieve universal modeling,
but you just achieve
universal modeling,
and you cannot achieve the
best performance on any task.
So the diffusion
method actually wins
the game of image generation,
and not the autoregressive.
Although in the MLP domain
the autoregressive method
is dominant, but in
image generation,
the winner is diffusion.
So what is a diffusion?
Diffusion is a totally different
self-supervised learning method
compared to
autoregressive methods.
You can also think it's a
autoregressive on a Fourier
domain or something like that.
But actually it's the DDPM is
the original paper of diffusion
model.
It's still the most popular
framework of diffusion modeling.
We can define a lot of
steps as we gradually
add in noise to a
clean image and we
get different
intermediate states
and train your model to predict
the noise, the original image,
or something like v [INAUDIBLE]
of the angle of the [INAUDIBLE]
and are actually given the
noisy input, noisy image.
So it's totally different,
but the most advantage
of differential model
or autoregressive model
is that during sampling, we
can use full utility of GPUS
because in our regressive
model, when we decode the token,
we actually wasted
the power of the GPU.
The utility of GPU is very low
if the batch size is small,
the batch size equal to 1.
But for diffusion model,
we just input all the image
into the model so it
can utilize the GPU
and it can sample it much faster
than autoregressive model.
The Relay Diffusion
Model is our recent work.
It solves the
problem in diffusion
about the noise scatter
across different resolution.
The first thing is you can see
the last image is actually three
images with the same noise.
The A and B are two images
with different resolution
and with the same noise level.
But the A is actually
more blurred for us
during the observation.
The problem is we add
an independent noise.
And actually, the
original signal, the image
is not independent
across the space.
So what we need to
do is if we want
to transform a noisy
schedule from low resolution
to high resolution, we
need to use a block noise
to find the equivalence on
the high-resolution images.
And finally, we can keep the SNR
in the frequency graph the same.
So using this method, we can
disentangle the noisy schedule
and the actually network
we use for diffusion.
Using noisy schedule, we don't
care about the resolution.
We just use a block noise when
we want to continue diffusion
on high resolution.
So the speed can
improve because we
don't need to generate the
image from the high resolution,
from the condition on
the low-resolution image,
high resolution fits.
And we also scale up the
Relay Diffusion to CogView3
after the paper.
CogView3 is actually a
large diffusion model.
And after distillation,
it could be very fast
because of the effectiveness
of the Relay Diffusion.
Finally, we get to something
relevant to our topic,
transformer.
And actually, the previous
works about diffusion is Unet,
and using transformer is
not trivial in diffusion.
The first work I think maybe is
solid enough is DiT from Meta.
The author of this paper is
also the author with ours.
So the most difference between
the original transformer
and this DiT is
the ada layer norm.
Ada layer norm is
predict a scale and bias
for different layer norm.
And scale shifts for different
layer norm conditioning
on the timestamp.
It's actually needs a very
huge amount parameters,
as the systems of hidden size
nearly equal to QKV per layer,
but the input is only 1 int.
1 int is actually very strange
because the input is only 1 int,
and you need millions of
parameters to transform it.
So there's some method can
reduce this thing in practice.
The Stable Diffusion
3 released recently.
It use another
architectures called MM-DiT.
The Stable Diffusion
3 first used
our released CogVLM to recaption
all the model-- all the images
and train a latent
diffusion model using
this new architecture.
The new architecture seem
like very complicated,
but the most important thing is
they use vision and text experts
like CogVLM instead of cross
attention to T5 features
like the previous ones.
So finally, we will talk
shortly about video generation,
because Sora is a currently
very popular thing.
We published a video generation
work several years ago.
Final version is
published on ICLR.
So it's maybe the first
open-source language
model for text-to-video
generation,
but the performance is much
worse than the current Sora
because it's autoregressive.
So using diffusion,
we can get better.
We're currently also working for
replication of Sora-like models,
and we can summarize that
the improvement of Sora
account from this
aspect, the forces.
There's no flaking
in the videos.
It can generate
high-quality images.
The first one, so
the deflickering,
can be solved by the 3D
latence encoder-decoder.
And if you train your diffusion
decoder, it could better.
The high quality is
thanks to the scaling up.
And it requires a
very high resolution.
And this is something related
to the long context fine
tuning and context
parallel techniques
in the language
model Infra, which
I introduced at the
beginning of this course.
So the most important
thing is they
use the Infra, they use Infra
in language model training
into the diffusion and make
it very easy to scale up
and scale up much larger
than the other companies.
And finally, the most important
thing is data coverage.
It's need a very
heavy data engineering
and the video recaption.
So I have introduced many
topics of current multimodality
[INAUDIBLE] and some problems
in this transformer community.
So there are some trends I think
will happen in one or few years
in the multimodality area.
In the next one or two
years, we can easily
recognize grounding all
the common-sense attributes
and human expressions and lots
of high-level vision scenes.
And all these things
will be very cheap
and be basically solved.
So this will happen
in one or two years.
At that time, the long
tail problem of autodriving
could be alleviated.
Not solved, but
largely alleviate.
And the second prediction
is the video understanding
will become very important
in the next one or two years,
because it's very useful.
We have lots of videos in the
internet and in our everyday
life, but it's very hard and
currently we cannot understand
very well.
And the most powerful video
understanding model currently
is Gemini 1.5,
but it's basically
lots of hallucinations and wrong
counting and lots of weakness.
So there's a very
large room to improve.
Another thing is we have enough
compute to deal with video now,
and especially in the
next one or two years
because the next generation of
NVIDIA GPU and the requirements
from the larger language model.
And another important
thing is embodied AI.
Embodied AI will be more and
more important in the research,
and it will be very closely
related to multimodality
research, although it cannot
impact our real life in a few
years.
Because we now have planning
ability with large language
models, we can recognize all
the same vision language models,
and there will be
some chances to get
some new ability and a
very astonishing demo
of this embodied AI.
But they may be very expensive
and cannot be used for everyday
life.
So what should we
do at that time?
For me, some researcher like
me in a large language model
company, we got enough
computer resources.
But for others, so I think if
you are a senior researcher,
so just follow your
heart and ignore me.
If you want to quickly gain
some citations, papers, impacts,
I think maybe you can consider
that the video understanding
models, data sets,
benchmarks, especially data
sets and benchmarks,
is very important
and in great need of the
video understanding community.
And for multimodality,
there is another topic
I haven't talked
about in this lecture.
It's the speech or audio.
I recently learned some
knowledge about audio,
and I lead the group of
speech AI group in Zhipu AI.
So I'm not a
researcher about audio,
but I can say that the
speech AI is underestimated.
It's actually very important for
the user need and application,
but there is no enough
GPU and researchers
put into this areas
like in language model.
Finally, if you want
to do some very useful
and impact AI research,
which is very risky,
advice is you need to make some
system PhD student at once,
because the best algorithm
must utilize the current GPU
and other hardware.
So you just need to know
some system PhD students.
Another that's more
difficult but influential
is there's actually some
room for new architectures
for some self-supervised
learning and optimizers,
because the next
generation of hardware
will be totally different.
So maybe the transformer will
have some competitors and also
the autoregressive
modeling method.
So there is some
room, but it's very
hard on some
computational resources.
And finally, the new
ways to transform compute
to high-quality data
is very important
because high-quality
web data is actually
be crawled down into almost
every large language model
company, and it's
currently not very enough.
So we need to find some new
ways to transform computes
to high-quality data.
For example, how to see sizings
in new data using code execution
results, using maybe
MCTS or reinforcement
learning or some other method.
It's very big area in
the last few years.
I think I will end this
lecture here, and thank you
for the instructors
and the audience,
and thank you very much.
If you have some question,
you can send email to this,
and I will answer
all the questions.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Thank you very much, Ming,
for the amazing talk and all
the useful advice.
So we have some questions.
I got one through Zoom, and
there's several also on Slido.
So Emily, are there
any in-person questions
from your end?
OK, if someone has some--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
--and you can type in the chat
in Zoom, if you are using Zoom.
Let me see.
OK, yeah.
Here are some questions
on Slido that I'll ask.
The first is that the success
of long context windows
must come at a cost.
What is this cost?
The cost very long
time consumption.
You just need to run
your inference engine
for a very long time.
Actually, the current inference
system of large language model
can be split into two periods.
One is profiling.
You need to import a very
long context into your engine.
And then another is decode.
And you generate
the token by token.
So most user case,
it actually not
generate a very long context,
and understand a long context
and generate a very few
tokens about the question.
So we can bear maybe one minute
to let the language model
to just run the long
context understanding
and then began to
answer your question.
So this is a course you
need to read for maybe
several seconds or one minute.
Yes.
Thank you.
I was muted, but yes.
Thanks.
That makes sense.
So there's two questions
which are pretty similar,
all upvoted on Slido, talking
about the quality of data.
So recently, folks have been
seeing that the quality of data
is what really determines final
model performance compared
to anything else.
Do you agree?
And related to
this, do you think
there's still a lot of
work to do around improving
the architecture of
models, or has attention
shifted to focus on data?
Yeah.
I think it's very
reasonable, actually,
what's the whole community
is doing to improve the data.
I just talk about this
opinion in the lecture.
It's the architecture,
the algorithm,
the data can conform
to each other.
If you have some idea, you
can inject the inductive bias
into architecture, you can
design a new algorithm,
and you can prepare some
data to tell your model
to act like that.
So many of the
very special cases
you can use data to
solve the problem.
So high-quality data
is more important
the architecture of this
for many tasks with that
and I think if you can find a
general update of transformer,
it's very valuable.
Just increase the power of
the model to fit in the data.
It's very valuable.
Yes.
All right.
Great.
Here's a question-- why is
autoregressive architecture
inferior to diffusion
in image generation?
Yeah.
It's very complicated.
This, question is very
complicated, actually.
So the diffusion is totally
different in autoregressive
to some extent.
But the most important thing I
have talked about in the lecture
is the speed of generation.
For autoregressive model, if
you use a very large model,
you train it for
a very long time,
I believe we can get
a very good result.
We can also generate
high-quality images
using autoregressive methods.
This is OK.
But the time to
generate an image
is very long because we need
to predict token by token.
Maybe a high-resolution image
is maybe thousands of tokens.
But for diffusion, we use
several steps of fast forwarding
all the image.
We don't need token
by token prediction,
as it would be thousands times
faster than autoregressive model
if you are generating
high-resolution images.
So this is a very
obvious advantage.
And for the modeling power, I
think the most important thing
is maybe some relation between
the space is actually not--
we are not modeling well
by autoregressive model
because the leftmost pixel
and the right bottom pixel
is very far in
autoregressive model.
But in diffusion
model, it's actually
they can see each other,
so it's not a problem.
But for the vision model,
it's have position problem,
so it's not easy to model in
a very complicated 2D spatial
problem.
This is also a possible reason,
but I cannot give a very good
answer about this question.
But yeah.
This would be more
research about that.
Thank you.
Right.
Great.
Thanks for the detailed answer.
So someone is asking,
how is the CogAgent model
different from the CogVLM model?
Yeah.
The CogAgent is actually fine
tuned from the CogView model.
But the CogAgent
model, they always
high resolution and web screen
cases because our motivation
is that the high-resolution
input for a web page
is very important because
there's many words, many icons,
something very
small, and you need
to use a very high-resolution
model to deal with it.
But if you just extend the
input resolution of CogVLM,
the consumption is very high, so
we use cross attention module,
adding to the CogVLM
to get CogAgent.
So this module is
much lightweight,
so we can deal with the
high resolution more easily.
Yeah.
Great.
Here's a question about video.
How do you think video
understanding will
aid AI's ability to have a
stronger physical understanding
of the world?
OK.
That's a very good question.
I think yes.
My answer is yes.
But actually, the actual problem
is because if you don't have
some data source which
contains physical rules,
you cannot train a good
video understanding model.
I think using the current real
language model pretraining
method because we need the
input, the text, image,
or text-video pairs to train.
And we actually did not use
any self-supervised learning
in the image or video, so we
cannot learn any knowledge from
pure video or image.
We're actually dealing
with annotated data
from the human side.
So if we want to
understand better
of the physical world
using annotated videos,
we need to find some new method
for self-supervised learning
or pretraining method.
This is a very good question.
Thank you.
All right.
OK.
A couple more questions.
Someone is asking,
are there VQA tasks
that involve multiple turns of
conversation in a tree structure
similar to a tree of thoughts
or a beam search style?
OK.
Yeah.
Maybe, but I still
think it's different.
And the tree of
thoughts could be
better because it's aware
of other mass information.
For example, the wrong
path, the other failed case,
something like that.
So my experience is
if you can include
all the contacts in your input,
you always get better results.
So yeah, maybe in
other tree of thought
or some other different
process, procedure,
and some other
informations, you just
included them into the
contents, the language model
will learn how to deal
with them and understand it
better than the beam search,
which is actually a hard code
master to compare
the probabilities.
It should be better
if you do it right.
Yes.
All right, thanks.
That's all the time
we have for questions.
So thanks again to Ming
for the great talk,
the detailed answers
to all the questions.